A Guide to the Louis O. Kunkel papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA172
Rockefeller Archive Center
Louis O. Kunkel papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1930-1959
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kunkel, Louis Otto
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA172
14.96 Cubic Feet
23 boxes; 11 wooden cases; 3 volumes
Biographical/Historical note
Louis Otto Kunkel, 1884-1960, at the RU (formerly RIMR) from 1931-1960. As Pathologist at the Bureau of Plant Industry, U.S. Department of Agriculture he conducted investigative work on virus diseases of the potato. As Associate Pathologist at the Hawaiian Sugar Planters' Association his studies were on viral diseases of sugar cane and their insect vectors. As Pathologist at the Boyce-Thompson Institute for Plant Research he developed a diversified program of studies on viral diseases of plants and became interested in the "yellows" type of plant diseases and the insect vectors involved in such disease. This general area of research constituted his main interest for the rest of his life. In 1931 Dr. Kunkel became head of RIMR Department of Plant Pathology at Princeton. In 1949 when Princeton laboratories were merged with New York City laboratories, he came to New York to continue his work. In 1956 he received the Certificate of Merit award at the Golden Jubilee meeting of the Botanical Society of America and in 1959 the Distinguished Service award of the New York Botanical Garden. His was a lifetime of outstanding research and administration in plant pathology, mainly in the field of virology.
Biographical note
1884 Born May 7 Audrain County near Mexico, Mo.
1909 B.S. in Education, State University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1910 A.B. State University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1911 A.M. State University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo. 1909-1911 Assistant in botany, State University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1911-1912 Graduate student, Washington University, St. Louis, Mo.
1911-1912 Research fellow in the Henry Shaw School of Botany, Washington University, St. Louis, Mo.
1912-1914 Graduate student, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1912-1913 Assistant in botany, Columbia University
1913-1914 Research assistant in botany, Columbia University
1914 Ph. D. Columbia University, N.Y.
1915-1916 Cutting traveling fellow from Columbia University
1914-1920 Pathologist, Bureau of Plant Industry, U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, Washington, D.C.
1920-1923 Associate pathologist, Hawaiian Sugar Planters' Association, Hawaii
1923-1931 Pathologist, Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research, Yonkers, N.Y.
1932 Elected member, National Academy of Sciences
1931-1949 Member and Head of Plant Pathology, RIMR Princeton, N.J.
1949-1955 Professor emeritus RU: Princeton and New York City laboratories merged
1955 Retired as administrator and devoted all of his time to research
1960 Died March 20 Newtown, Pa.
Awards
1956 Received the Certificate of Merit award at the Golden Jubilee meeting of the Botanical Society of America
1959 Distinguished Service award of The New York Botanical Garden
Member of: National Academy of Sciences, American Philosophical Society, Botanical Society of America, American Psychopathological Society, Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi, American Society of Naturalists, American Institute of the City of New York, Society of American Bacteriologists: (1942-1943 President of Theobald Smith Society, N.J. branch of; also on program committee), National Geographic Society (membership certificate with biographical material in Box no. 1), Torrey Botanical Club
Served as Member of the Board of National Research Fellowships in the Biological Sciences for the National Research Council, Member of the American Advisory Council for Yenching University at Peiping, China, Member of the Advisory Council of the Department of Biology, Princeton University, Member of the Committee to visit the Division of Biology for the Board of Overseers of Harvard College (1934-1941), Member of the Board of Managers (1952-1961) and member of the Scientific Committee (1953-1957) for the New York Botanical Garden, Member of Council of Awards of The American Institute of the City of New York, Associate editor of Phytopathology (1931-1934)
Family History. Parents: Mr. Henry Kunkel and Mrs. Katie Price (Spencer) Kunkel of Mexico, Mo., 1915 Sept. 4 married Johanna Caroline Wortmann, Children: (4 sons): Henry George, Otto Wortmann, Walter Ralph, Paul Spencer
Secondary sources for Louis O. Kunkel:
G.C. Ainsworth, Introduction to the history of plant pathology (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1981).
Includes biographical references, bibliography (arranged chronologically) and "Some landmarks in the history of plant pathology."
There are, however, two mistakes regarding Kunkel's appointment: 1) p. 95. Kunkel was not the first Director of the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology. Carl Ten Broeck was director (not the first; Theobald Smith, 1916), appointed in 1930. Kunkel was appointed director of the Division of Plant Pathology, 1931. 2) p. 139. In 1935 Kunkel was no longer at the Boyce Thompson Institute, but at RIMR.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Louis Otto Kunkel were deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives on 1975 by RU plant Pathology Department.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 K963
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical material, subject files, notes, slides, negatives, and reprints.
Biochemistry; Agriculture; Pathology; Plant viruses; Plant diseases; Diseases; Medical education; Chemistry; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences
- Biographical material, 1884-1965; 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal and career development correspondence; obituary material; photographs; annual reports to corporation.
  - Personal correspondence and biographical sketches, 1930-1959; 2 folders
    - 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes correspondence. with E.B. Smith and Simon Flexner leading to L.O. Kunkel appointment as Member of RIMR Princeton with Flexner, Smith and Kunkel holographs.
      Including: Letters of congratulations on appointment as Head of Plant Pathology, RIMR Princeton and on being elected Member of the National Academy of Sciences (Includes letters from W.V.J. Osterhaut and C.S. Gager).
      - Vita - [Original copy L.O. Kunkel to E.B. Smith with corrected copy], 1930 December 19
      - Who's Who in America, circa 1930s
      - news item announcing appointment as head of Plant Pathology, RIMR Princeton, 1931 April 6
      - 1932 July 1, 21. Theobald Smith holographs about diseased pine trees with 1932 July 8 Kunkel reply, 2 items
    - 1933-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - National Geographic membership certificate, 1933 February 7
      - typescript of Science Service radio talk "Pests away from home", 1933 March 31
      - reprint of "Aster yellows and its control". A brief summary of the work of L.O. Kunkel in solving an important growers' problem by Zeliaette Troy of Boyce Thompson Institute, 1935 October
      - correspondence with F. Weinstein [Photocopy], 1936 February 27
      - Who's Who in the Western Hemisphere, 1943
      - Curriculum vitae listing, Member emeritus, circa 1949
      - typescripts of lectures delivered at Cornell University, Ithaca, NY as visiting lecturer: "Summaries of discussions of plant virus diseases" and "The nature of viruses", 1953 March
      - correspondence. with Day and Zimmerman - biographical sketch for government security clearance, 1954 June 8
      - statement of Kunkel research work at RIMR for archives, 1955 September 23
      - National Academy of Sciences meeting at RIMR. Typescripts of abstract and paper delivered "Acquired immunity from infection by strains of aster-yellows virus in the aster leafhopper" with typescript of Kunkel demonstration, 1957 November 18-20
  - Bibliography and photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kunkel bibliography (1912-1961, 9 pages) and Kunkel photographs 1931, 1948, 1956, 9 pages
  - Annual reports to corporation (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Some plant disease work currently in progress", undated
      Includes Holmes, Braun, Kunkel work.
    - L.O. Kunkel and associates, Plant Pathology, 1949 October 1
      Includes: "Further studies on crown gall; mutants from non-systemic strains of tobacco mosaic virus; aster yellows virus retained during life of the vector regardless of length of feeding period on diseased plants"
  - Obituary material (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - RU News
    - New York Times, 1960 March 21
    - Herald Tribune, 1960 March 21
    - Letter of appreciation for sympathy expressed from Betty Kunkel (Henry Kunkel's wife). Received, 1960 April 11
    - Biographical memoirs 38 (1965) 145-1960 by Wendell M. Stanley, 1960-1965
    - Louis Otto Kunkel, 1884-1960 by Francis O. Holmes Phytopathology 50 (1960) 777-778
- Rockefeller University Administration: Subject Files, 1931-1959; 2
  - Administrative correspondence
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in alphabetical order as to administrative department and then in chronological order.
    - Announcements and special events (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bursar's office, 1947-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Correspondence primarily with Charles Petrezelka concerning expenses.
    - Business Manager; Assistant; Others Correspondence, 1931-1955; 3 folders
      Primarily with E.B. Smith and some with W.B. Flinn about building and laboratory construction; personnel; staff appointments; salaries; budgets and expenditures; publications; grants-in-aid to various journals; attending RIMR NYC seminars and luncheons.
      - 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 1940-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Includes special interest items: 1942 June 22-27. 75th anniversary celebration of the Torrey Botanical Club. Dr. Kunkel RIMR representative. 1955 Sept. 23 typescript copy of statement to Dr. Rivers "Summary of researches of L.O. Kunkel." [Original in Box no. 1].
    - Directors; President, 4 folders
      Arrangement in chronological order as to Director or President
      - Director: Flexner, Simon, 1931-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Correspondence about staff appointments; Meeting: 1931 Oct. 30 RIMR Trustees Annual meeting. Paper delivered on plant pathology; National Research Council grant recommendation for Professor Vinson.
        Includes statement on "Incubation periods of plant viruses in insect vectors" for Dr. Flexner and congratulations on Dr. Flexner 80 birthday.
      - Directors: Gasser, Herbert S., 1937-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Correspondence about staff appointments; Gasser letter of appreciation on AAAS awards to members of Kunkel department; promotion recommendation for Armin Braun with report of Braun's investigative work and summary of Karl Maramoroch's investigative work.
        Includes 1939 Oct. 18 list of scientific contributions of Kunkel department on "Plant diseases".
      - Director: Rivers, Thomas M. (Director 1953-1955), 1932-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Correspondence about plant virus exhibit on 1935 Apr 18 American Assoc. of Pathologists and Bacteriologists/American Assoc. of Immunologists meeting on Virus symposium. Meeting: 1942 May Ithaca, N.Y. Cornell Univ. Messenger lectures. Paper delivered "New hosts as a key to progress in plant virus disease research".
      - President: Bronk, Detlev W., 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Correspondence about invitations to meet new scientific staff; announcement of new electronic and instrument shops:.
        Includes duplicated material on 1956-1957 RIMR Pamphlet.
    - Librarians: Trask, Lillian; Judkins, Esther. Correspondence, 1931-1952 (?) (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Primarily about purchasing journals and books.
    - Personnel; Vacations (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Princeton Branch: Smillie, E.W., 1932-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Correspondence about attending Bd. of Scientific Directors' luncheons at Princeton (some Correspondence with E.B. Smith); personnel; vacations; travel allowance; equipment; construction costs
    - Princeton Branch: Ten Broeck, Carl, Director, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, 1931-1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Correspondence about visits to Princeton; personnel; scientific staff and appointments; laboratory equipment; annual reports; journals.
      Includes special interest items: Lecture: 1932 Mar 21 RIMR Princeton staff seminar; 1932 Oct. 24 brief biographical and work outline of Holmes, Osborn, Stanley, White, Price, Spencer, Thornberry, Jensen, Plantenga; recommendations for T. Laskaris; A.F. Blakeslee; I.P. Norval; report and praise of Braun investigative work 1938-1941; Ten Broeck holographs.
      Includes Correspondence with M. Swift/ Ten Broeck concerning Pinus Bunglana and the Gundstone Tamopan.
    - Purchasing, 1932-1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Correspondence primarily with C.P. Spies and some with E.H. Turner about purchasing laboratory and greenhouse equipment and supplies.
    - Publications, 1933-1943 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Correspondence with E.C. Campbell and F.M. Stewart concerning Dr. Kunkel and staff publications.
- Correspondence, 1930-1959; 3
  Early correspondence is addressed to Dr. Kunkel at Boyce Thompson. Correspondence deals largely with an exchange of scientific information about plant virus diseases, exchange of samples of diseased and healthy plants for experimental purposes and identification, and an exchange of samples of cultures and seeds. Further correspondence is about attendance to scientific meetings and frequent presentation of papers. Dr. Kunkel attends many meetings of the American Phytopathological Society and American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS).
  Includes Correspondence about manuscripts for publication and many requests for reprints of Kunkel published papers; many job inquiries. Dr. Kunkel displays a keen sense of humor with friends.
  Includes some administrative Correspondence relating to staff appointments (filed under name of appointee).
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - A-Am (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Academic Press, 1955; 21 items
      Correspondence with Academic Press and Max Lauffer, Editor; contract with Academic Press; notice to contributors; printer's page proof of contribution; advertising leaflet of Vol. 1, Advances in Virus Research. Manuscript: In relation to chapter title "Cross-protection between strains of yellow-type viruses" in Vol. III Advances in Virus Research 1955 pp. 251-273.
    - Adams, J.B., 15 items
      About supplying cultures of aster leafhopper, Macrosteles divisus
    - Adams, J.F., 2 items
    - Adsuar, J., 1 item
    - Agee, H.P., 3 items
    - Agnew, T.W., 2 items
    - Alabama Agricultural Experiment Station, 1 item
    - Albritton, E.C., 3 items
    - Allen, D.F., 4 items
    - Allen, D.H., 2 items
      Comments on use of biological warfare by Russians.
    - Allington, W.B., 4 items
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS). Correspondence with S. Woodley and J. Mayer, 4 items
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1938 June; 48 items (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Meeting: 1938 June Ottawa symposium of AAAS on genetics of pathogenic organisms. Correspondence deals with editing of symposium papers for publication.
      Includes Correspondence about Kunkel paper.
      Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent.
      - Coker, R.E., 14 items
      - Konst, H., 2 items
      - Moulton, F.R., 5 items
      - Riker, A.J., 8 items
      - Stakman, E.C., 17 items
      - Taliafero, NH (Huff, C.G.), 2 items
    - American Association of Economic Entomologists, 4 items (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Correspondence with E.V. Walters and E.N. Cory on symposium.
    - American Association of Immunologists/American, 1961 January-June; 11 items (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists joint program.
      Meeting: N.Y.C. Cornell University Medical College Symposium on virus diseases. Correspondence deals with exhibit and paper.
      Includes abstract.
    - American Association of Immunologists, 1938 (?) (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Meeting: Atlantic City, N.J. Concerns abstract.
    - American Cancer Society, 1952 March 3-5 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Meeting: 2nd National Cancer Conference, Cincinnati, Ohio. Correspondence deals with discussion of papers by others.
    - American Council on Education. On ranking graduate schools in the field of plant pathology, 4 items (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - American Desert Tea Co., 3 items (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - American Institute of Chemists, 2 items (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - American Institute of the City of NY, 1932-1957; 80 items (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Correspondence deals with: Membership; Roundtable discussion participant arrangements for others; Member of Council on awards: includes by-laws of Council; workings as Council member (voting); recommendations for W.M. Stanley for possible gold medal award with Stanley bibliography and vitae; typescript of account on scientific work of Wm. Crocker, receipient of 1938 gold medal award by L.O. Kunkel.; On judging committee of the American Institute School Science Fair in 1952. Dr. Kunkel member until 1955.
    - American Journal of Botany, 3 items (Box 4, Folder 5)
      (See also under; Trelease, Bot. Soc. Am. Box no. 15 and Meyer, B.S. Editor Box no. 11).
    - American Midland Naturalist, 2 items (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - American Patent System, 3 items (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1942-1959; 40 items (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Biographical/Historical note
      Became member in 1942.
      Includes recommendations for F.G. Merkle for APS grant; recommendation for P.W. Zimmerman for APS membership with bibliography.
    - American Phytopathological Society, 1931-1957; 72 items (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Deals with workings as member of Society.
      Includes Correspondence about: Phytopathology (publication); presenting papers at Society meetings; Society membership; comments on classification and nomenclature of plant viruses; exhibit for 50 anniversary society meeting.
  - Am-Ar (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - American Society of Naturalists, 1932-1947; 13 items
      Became member in 1932.
    - American Weekly, 1 item
    - Anderson, C.W., 2 items
    - Anderson, E.J., 2 items
    - Anderson, F.P., 1 item
    - Anderson, H.W., 1932-1946; 25 items
      Includes recommendation for Kenneth S. Chester.
    - Anderson, J.A., 1 item
    - Anderson, P.J., 2 items
      Recommendation for E.L. Spencer
    - Andrews, C.H., 2 items
      Comments on nomenclature of viruses
    - Annand, P.N., 3 items
    - Annual Review of Microbiology., 7 items
      Correspondence deals with papers for Vol 1, Nov. 1947
    - Antikajian, G., 3 items
    - Apostolides, C.A., 2 items
    - Appleman, C.O., 1934-1940; 6 items
      Includes recommendation for George L. McNew.
    - Archives of Biochemistry, 6 items
    - Arizona Agricultural Experiment Station, 1 item
    - Armstrong, Geo. M., 1 item
  - Ar-Ay (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Arnaudi, C., 2 items
    - Arthur, J.M., 11 items
    - Artschwager, E., 4 items
    - Associated Hospital Service of N Y, 2 items
    - Atoms for Peace Award. Invitation but declines, 1 item
    - Auchter, E.C., 2 items
    - Avery, G.S., 1935-1949; 12 items
      Includes recommendation for Lindsay Black.
    - Avery, O.T., 2 items
    - Aycock, W.L., 2 items
  - B-Ba (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bache-Wug, S., 2 items
    - Bachelder, S., 4 items
    - Bachrach, H.L., 2 items
    - Badger, R.G., 2 items
      Congratulations on Kunkel radio talk on "Pests away from home"
    - Bailey, I.W., 2 items
    - Bailey, L.H., 1 item
    - Baker, K.F., 1933-1942; 4 items
    - Baker, W.L., 2 items
    - Bald, J.G., 1935-1955; 4 items
    - Barail, L.C., 2 items
    - Barbour, E.E. Senator., 1 item
      Recommendation for F.A. Varrelman for Directorship of U.S. Botanical Gardens
    - Barker, H.D., 1936-1947; 6 items
    - Barr & Sons, 2 items
    - Barss, H.P., 1931-1950; 28 items
      Includes letters of congratulations on Kunkel work and leadership.
    - Bartholomew, R.P., 2 items
      Recommendation for E.L. Spencer.
    - Bartlett, H.H., 2 items
    - Bartlett Tree Research Laboratories, 1 item
    - Bartley, C.E., 7 items
    - Barton, L.V., 5 items
    - Bausch and Lomb Optical Co., 5 items
    - Bawden, F.C., 6 items
    - Bayard, A.W., 2 items
  - Be-Ben (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Beale, H.P., 1933-1957; 32 items
      Includes recommendation for Guggenheim fellowship.
    - Bear, F.E., 4 items
    - Beckenbach, J.R., 1 item
      Recommendation for Folke Johnson.
    - Becker, C. Inc., 1 item
    - Becker, G.G., 2 items
    - Bell, A.T., 1 item
    - Bell, R.H., 3 items
    - Bell, T.C., 3 items
    - Bellini, C.C., 1 item
    - Benda, G.T., 11 items
    - Benedict, R.C., 2 items
    - Bennett, C.W., 1932-1945; 24 items
    - Bennett, J.P., 2 items
    - Benson, L.C., 2 items
    - Bentley, G.M., 2 items
  - Ber-Bi
    - Berg, C.M., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Berger Mfg. Co., 1 item (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bergman, H.F., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Berkeley, G.H., 1934-1951; 28 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Berry, G.P., 1 item (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bhargava, K.S., 7 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bicknell, A.K., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Biekart, H.M., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Biological Abstracts, 6 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Includes typescripts of abstracts prepared by Dr. Kunkel on: R.N. Mather paper "Leaf-curl in Zinnia elegans et Dehra Dun (holograph of abstract); Kenneth H. Smith book "Recent advances in the study of plant viruses"; comments on value of Biological Abstracts.
    - Birkeland, J.M., 9 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bischopp, F.C., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bishop, C.F., 4 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bitancourt, A., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Black, Lindsay M. At RIMR 1937-1946, 1934-1959; 120 items (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Professional Correspondence between colleagues socially friendly (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Includes recommendation for; 2 Black holographs.
    - Blakeslee, A.F., 1936-1952; 68 items (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Professional Correspondence between friendly colleagues (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Includes request to work at Princeton branch of RIMR on retirement from Carnegie Institution at Cold Spring Harbor - request denied; 4 Blakeslee holographs; recommendation for Margaret B. Dunham.
  - Bl-Bo (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Blair, J.C., 2 items
      Recommendation for H.H. Thornberry
    - Blake, M.A., 1936-1946; 13 items
    - Blakiston Co. Inc., 3 items
      Correspondence about Kunkel chapter in "The Dynamics of Virus and Rickettsial Infections"
    - Blanchard, G.A., 2 items
    - Blandy Experimental Farm, 10 items
      Correspondence with P.W. Zimmerman, C.C. Little, J.L. Newcombe and O.E. White.
      Includes reports by Kunkel and others. Dr. Kunkel is a member of Advisory Committee.
    - Blau, Max & Sons, 2 items
    - Blodgett, E.O., 5 items
    - Blood, H.L., 1934-1941; 7 items
    - Blue Anchor, 2 items
    - Blumenthal, W., 2 items
      About T. Laskaris draft status
    - Blumer, S., 6 items
      Includes Kunkel holograph.
    - Board of Vocational Guidance, 1 item
    - Bodger, E.M., 2 items
    - Bodine, E.W., 2 items
    - Bohme, R.L., 9 items. 2 items in German; 1 Kunkel handwritten note
  - Bo (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bold, H.C., 3 items
      RI representative of 75 anniversary celebration of the Torrey Botanical Club
    - Bonar, L., 2 items
      Recommendation for R.L. Steere.
    - Bonde, R., 2 items
    - Bonn, M., 2 items
    - Bonner, J., 2 items
    - Booij, H.L., 1 item
    - Boothroyd, C.W., 2 items
    - Borodin, D., 14. items